Basically uh we're going to go into
the whole thing is uh I think most
people who are not into uh you know
machine learning and the research side
of things uh we might see some like
diffusion models for image generation
but it's primarily large language models
with stocastic gradient descent uh which
I can go into detail about explaining
that if anybody wants to later but um
the kind of goal for this is to go over
uh stuff in kind of two phases that
aren't that. And we are going to get
into diffusion. Uh and this is very much
uh I'll be sharing this uh repo uh
online uh afterwards. And um it has
links for further reading. Um and I do
apologize some of the later part of this
is uh was scaffolded by AI and then
written by AI and I haven't gone through
and uh been able to uh clean up a lot of
that. So I'll be doing that after. um
this meeting, you know, kind of doing
area of improvement over this this
evening. Kind of ran out of time. Uh but
yeah, the idea is to kind of do a
surface level kind of conceptual uh uh
understanding of each of these and then
we'll go into uh further reading or
there will be further reading in the
book and and also a little bit of
history in there too.
Um, so one of the first ones was Alpha
Go. Um, and you know, we had this uh
Beat Blue was 1997.
I think it was 1997. Yeah. Um, that uh
beat uh the grandm world grandmaster at
chess.
Who was it? Anybody?
Yeah. Uh, and so that was kind of an
unthinkable thing, right? But then, you
know, we started thinking about it. I
said, well, you know, there are really
distinct rules for chess. The the move
set is pretty exact as far like there is
generally a best move you can do or a
series of like one to three best moves.
Uh, right. So, maybe that's not as
impressive in retrospect, but then go,
go is this like very nuanced game,
right? Uh, you're talking about like uh
more feeling based things like who has
the most territory, what what's the sway
look like? You know, uh the rule set is
tremendously bigger than chess. So that
was like, oh, there's no way that a
computer is ever going to be able to do
that. Well, then uh Alph Go comes along.
So, um, the way that Alph Go was made
is, uh, they basically took a lot of the
Go games, uh, from the world champions
and they fed it into this system. And
the system would do a Monte Carlo
research, which what that means, uh, to
kind of break that down into human
language
is that it will kind of, uh, figure out
pathways. So, it's a a tree of like all
the different decisions. So, think of
like Spock uh knowing being like 10
steps ahead of everybody else. He can
see like all these different pathways
can go down uh to kind of get to an
instate of whatever uh the situation is
right now. And he can kind of go through
those in his mind and figure out which
one is the best and weight those higher
and basically go through all these
branches the tree be like, "Oh yeah,
this one's good. This one's good. Uh
these are not so good." You can stop,
you know, ignore those now. And you can
it gets more and more efficient that
way. Right? So, uh it basically was
going through these games looking at all
of the different moves and kind of
calculating the next moves and how good
they would be and it would be going so
many steps ahead. And that was uh one of
the parameters of the model was like how
many steps ahead it goes. Now, the other
thing they did is this was kind of an
early form of attention. So, not only
would it judge those moves in that game,
but it would look at other games that
were had a similar setup and compare
moves from those games and you kind of
had a a cross reference between
different games to bring in that sense
of generalization.
Um,
yeah. So the policy net uh it had a
built-in policy net that was uh almost
an algorithmic um way of scoring the
moves and that would drive the the tree
search Monte Carlo tree search to weight
them higher or lower like ah this is a
good decision this is a good move or
maybe not so much with that one.
Um and then alpha zero came along after
that. So uh alpha go beat lease at all.
Um
was that 2012 I want to say
2016 okay
um so be at least it all um one of the
interesting things was move 37.
Uh and this kind of uh in retrospect
came from that cross referential search
between different games and kind of that
generalization where whenever it made
move 37
uh I think least at all had to go out
and take a smoke break.
Yeah.
Because he didn't understand it and all
of the people who were judging that
competition were like oh dumb AI has
made a mistake.
And then later on down the road, it
turned out that move was a pivotal move
for the game. I think that was game two
that it did that game two. And so that
brings up one thing that is uh really
interesting to think about with these
very deep neural networks. And kind of
the definition uh of generative uh
mathematically speaking is that the data
features and what I mean by that is if
you have a house for instance it'll have
square footage that is one data feature.
It'll have uh walkability that's another
uh data could be another data feature.
Um you know so on so forth. The price
would be a data feature. So each of
these aspects of the house for sale
tail, right? With a a deep neural
network, you don't have to define those
data features, it will find those uh
basically by itself. And that's kind of
where the black box part of it comes
from, right? So
this goes into that that move 37. It saw
some pattern that uh the master human
play had not seen, you know, in all of
the thousands of years. I think the
Chinese game, right? All the thousands
of years we played go, nobody had really
seen that and they thought it was stupid
actually, but then it turned out to be
great. Um, after that along came Alpha
Zero, which Alpha Zero was a slight
modification on Alpha Go. And what that
did is they threw out I mentioned it was
loaded up with all the human games,
right? They threw that out. They're
like, "We don't we don't have any of
that. We don't these silly humans don't
even know how to play Go. You couldn't
beat us." I'm speaking as AI, right? But
um
they threw that out and they had it play
against itself from scratch, from ground
zero.
And it got even better, even faster
because it did not have those human
constraints. You could think of it like
that. Um, to kind of weigh it down, it
didn't have that free learning. Yeah.
So,
was that was Alpha Zero also a Netflix
series just like Alpha Go?
I'm not sure
because I saw the Alpha Go series and I
thought it was pretty impressive when I
watched it back then.
Yeah. But I had I didn't know if they
actually televised or document document.
I'm not sure. That would be interesting
to to look into though.
Oh, also I should mention that uh I want
this to be like very much uh not a
lecture, a conversation. So feel free to
interrupt me, ask questions. Don't even
have to raise your hands like we can
talk, right?
Um
so
one thing that I uh kind of came to
understand with alpha or kind of thought
about with alpha zero is it's a really
good way to describe uh synthetic data.
I was describing uh trying to describe
to one of my friends what synthetic data
is. Well, this is one of the first
examples of synthetic data uh far before
we got to the point of like the whole
craze of like, oh, we're going to run
out of data and we're going to have to
start making synthetic data and it's
going to degrade over time and so on so
forth. Well, Alpha Zero is a proof of
concept that that's not the case, right?
Because it started from zero, started
from scratch. It didn't have any games
loaded into it. It just played against
itself over and over again with only the
rule set of go and the scoring system
and it learned the the best ways to win.
Um all of those games of it playing
against itself. That's synthetic data.
Isn't it u it seems like a kind of an
apples to oranges comparison because in
the case of go uh there's a winning and
losing and there's a certain you can
kind of discreetly tell whether a move
is better or worse but like uh what
works produced for example doesn't have
such a clear judgment that you can
assign that you give to it.
H so um
so with with the words I mean as I think
you know there's like uh the um uh what
is it block vector word vector word word
word vector um that you know has been
pre-trained with like where these words
are in a high dimensional latent space
um and with go it is actually more
ended, I think, than you would think
because there are not necessarily
discrete better moves. I mean, there are
because there's ones that win the game,
there's some that don't, but uh if
you've ever played uh it can get to more
of like a feel of like I feel like I've
got this territory under control. Uh,
and obviously I'm I'm not an expert
player, so I I can't really speak on it
um from an educated point, but I think
that there is a little bit more nuance
than you would imagine.
Certainly more than chess.
I played a little bit of go. It's the
decision space is absolutely massive.
Um, simpler stuff than chess, but in
case you don't know, 19 by 19 grid. Um,
that's more than four times what
and you can place your stone only one
type of piece but still
I'm familiar with uh with go a little
bit but I guess I'm thinking with words
for example sometimes you're lying on
purpose or you know you're creating I
don't know JSON that makes something I
don't know
there's a certain narrowness of a game
in terms of the
U insert smart sounding words here. I
kind of lost my train of thought. Sorry.
Well, I think that's kind of what move
37 was. It was a little bit of a big I
think might be
was the reward function um for the the
system set up to reward like only on the
winning condition at the end of the game
or was it rewarding at every turn?
Uh so that was part of the policy um
structure that they had the Monte Carlo
research.
So basically every uh and also with the
Monte Carlo research to get into a
little bit more detail um that kind of
does its own sort of like back
propagation. So it'll go like 10 moves
down a certain tree and it will see like
what the outcome is or in number of
moves down right and whatever that
outcome is the policy will judge it on
how good it is and it'll actually back
propagate that up through that decision
tree. So each that whole uh branching
structure is weighted higher. So it does
that as it goes. Yeah.
And that was a trained neuronet for for
that or was that like a deterministic? I
guess the Monte Carlo wouldn't be but
the policy net is a policy net a train
neuronet.
I'm not sure how not sure how
Monte Carlo just means that some of the
random after waiting.
Yeah. Um, so
probably just cons.
Yeah. So it it basically will uh and
there there's like different parameters
you can give to it, right, of like
there's obviously you can't look at the
every single possible move and go, but
you'll get like a set and it'll go
through do the waiting prune. Um there
will be some noise added in for like the
random pruning. Um but then it will
Yeah. And there's different algorithms
for it too, right?
All right.
Alpha fold. Um, alpha fold is uh really
interesting one. So um
there was uh the um
half 13 competition and I'm guessing a
lot of you are probably familiar with uh
fold at folding at home. That was part
of that competition, right? that was the
winning team for a number of years. Uh
I'd have to look up how many but uh they
they did a lot of great work with
folding at home which was distributed
computing to go through these different
algorithms for folding proteins and
figuring out the ones that work. Um
and uh so
what was it uh in 2018 Alpha Fold so it
had been going on since 1994. At 2018 uh
Alpha Fold uh was introduced and I
believe that first year it got up to
about 34 of the score of folding at
home. The next year it was far
surpassing it. Uh and graph of this it's
like you know like three quarters next
year it's like here's uh here's folding
at home here's alpha the year after that
I think it was the third year it was we
had salt uh protein folding and so this
one's really interesting because it kind
of does um three different
uh paradigms of well I'm using that word
too much it does three different things
for modeling the protein and again it
kind of does a cross as attention
between them. So you have the sequence
of protein, you have the shape of it and
then you have
the relationship to other proteins that
do similar things. So those three things
are kind of the three um parts that it
was trained on with uh being able to
look across those to see like you know
if I change uh this particular part of
the sequence uh it's going to mess
everything up because we can see that
how it messed everything up in this
other protein over here and um part of
it was a geometric uh model so it
actually had uh vector points to show
the geometry of the folded protein. And
so this uh starts to get us into
uh
geometric models which lead into world
models, right? Like where you actually
have this three-dimensional space. There
can be properties within uh points on
that space. Like I'm not a biologist,
but I think with protein folding there
is kind of a a string structure and
there's flat structure. I think one of
them is called beta something and the
other one's called something else. But
it can kind of know like the properties
of each of those at each point in that
fold. It can also then uh in kind of a
latent representational space um put
those compare those uh two different
proteins together to see like what the
differences are uh in the spatial
representation of them. So, it's I mean
it's like taking Lego blocks and and
actually building something out and
being able to compare it to another Lego
truck that you made, right?
Um,
right.
It won a Nobel Prize uh because proteins
are kind of the machinery of us and all
of these things. They shared the Nobel
Prize with the um people who were
running the holding at home function, I
believe. Um but yeah, not only can it
solve for all of the proteins that we
know of, but it can make new ones as
well. Um it can synthesize new proteins
that have a high likelihood of being
viable proteins.
Any questions or discussion on that?
Um yeah, I've never done bio. I just
think it's just a really hard
combinatorial problem though.
Exactly. Yeah. It's like
Okay.
I I think the uh solving for the uh
sequence was pretty easy, but then they
realized that actually it is like actual
physical kind of machinery and how it
works. So how it's folded is very very
important. And when they started looking
into that it it was combinatorial
explosion.
And it was kind of that uh looking
across uh the different proteins that do
similar things and how they're folded
and how they work. I think that's kind
of the that was the secret blackbox
thing that got Alpha P to really
essentially solve for it.
All right. Stable diffusion. Um
so
stable diffusion well so diffusion
models first of all
uh they're used for image generational a
lot um and just to kind of give you a
simple example of how they're trained
you
and uh this is not one of my areas of
expertise I'll I'll get to my my
wheelhouse when we get to the
evolutionary stuff But you basically
have an image, you add noise, Gaussian
noise to it. What I mean by Gossian
noise just
you don't have to worry about it.
Yes, static static noise um more or less
on a Gossian a bell curve um depending
on where you're at in it. So it's kind
of randomized in that way. But yeah,
you're just you're adding static to an
image over many many different steps and
you keep each one of those steps, right?
So you know you have like the whole line
of how this random noise was added which
it's random. So at some certain point
you would think if it's random how could
you how could you get back to the
original image weird right? But we found
that if you uh actually train models on
a step-by-step basis,
giving it that static uh that most
static image um knowing that you have
generated that static image from an
original image and you just show them
like you need to get to this next one
and then you need to get to this next
one and then you need to get to this
next one, next one, next one, next one
until they get to your original and
okay, you converge. Stop.
doing that with enough images which
that's a really easy process to uh do.
you just you can get any number of you
know millions of images and break them
down in that way and then you have a
model it's usually uh convolutional uh
layers of that which not going to get
into the details of that uh at least not
during the main talk here but basically
it looks over the image um I just lost
my train now too
where was I at
this scale stuff the
Yeah. Yeah. So, it can it can be used
for a lot of different things besides
just image generation. Um, and it's
actually kind of the foundation of
energy based models too. But yeah, you
you get millions of images, you add the
static to them, you train the model on
each of these and it learns those
patterns and then you can give it uh you
can intermingle that with words and say
like so you say like if I describe this
image, it should look like this and you
can take it through that entire loop,
right? And so you eventually get to the
point with image generation where you're
like, "Give me a summer day with a blue
balloon in the sky or I don't know, and
bees flying through the air and uh
there's a river off in the distance."
And it knows to kind of uh how to
generate that image from just taking
doing it step by step, right? So it just
each step at a time, it takes out a
little bit more static and you can
actually see um this process happening
if you uh run one locally and there's
some tools to like break it down. It's
really interesting to see uh there's
lots of animations out there online too
of like how it kind of looks on the in
between the intermediate steps. Um I
remember that uh when they train them
it's I was I remember reading
that they train them based on the target
image and not
so like even though let's say they're 10
steps away that they would still say
like I want the target image and they
would pass that back in rather than like
a stepped version and what they're
really trying to do I think was like
prevent overshooting or something like
that where they would like try to dial
it in so so much all in one shot and
that's where I think all the steps came
like that they they tried to do with
just like one at first like it wasn't
really working and so they just did it
in smaller increments to prevent like I
guess overfitting the model
Gota. I'm not sure about that, but that
would make sense. That's kind of like
gradient descent, right? Where you take
one little step and you have a learning
rate um each time. Um and what you might
be talking about is uh kind of later
with stable diffusion. So what I was
describing is just kind of diffusion in
general.
Um with stable diffusion, they actually
added in a lot of things to make it more
scalable and work better. One of the
things to edit in was uh to look for
patterns. So that's where you get like
the edges and the uh the vectors and
stuff like that where it's like it it
will see that pattern and it will kind
of tuck away like how to make that
pattern so that it can do that in guess
a compressed way. That's a really bad
way of saying it, but
excuse me. Um,
so I I guess to use kind of like a
metaphor here, uh, stable diffusion, you
could imagine it as you're in you're in
a foggy forest and you can't see even
like 2 feet in front of you. And, uh,
within this forest, there is every
possible image uh, you can imagine,
right? And so, but you can't see them
because they're off through the top. But
uh what stable diffusion is, it's kind
of like a compass where it's like I want
this kind of an image and the compass
will point the direction. You take a
step there and like all right cool now
go to the right a little bit. You take a
step that way and eventually you come
through the fog and you see the exact
image that you were looking for.
Do you want to explain what it means for
the adversarial?
Ah yes.
So, uh,
generative adversarial network, that's
interesting. I thought it was, uh,
whatever I said earlier,
but uh,
so whenever we first started coming out
with agents, we had like one of the
reasons why they were so powerful is
that you could have one agent, it would
check another one, right?
So you could have an agent go and do a
task like uh come up with I don't know a
block of code and then another agent
would look at that block of code even
run it and be like no your code is [__]
try again. And so they're basically
going back and forth until it gets to a
certain threshold of how good the code
is and it's like all right user here's
your code your beautiful code right so
uh a generative adversarial network is
like that but at a lower level at the
actual um level of the the model layers
itself. So what what this will look like
is um there's like a a recurrent neural
network basically meaning the output
feeds back into the input. Um basically
you add a step in there where it can
judge that output before it goes back
before it feeds back in. And there's
also different types of uh adversarial
networks too. Um like there's one where
it will go it will do the full forward
pass. What I mean by forward pass is it
goes from the input of the model to the
encoding through all the neural network
decoding and actually the output step
and then it will have another model that
is like the judge. Um now
lots of times it won't actually even
decode it because it doesn't need to to
get to like human readable thing. It'll
get to that like pre uh uh decoding
step, pass it off to that uh the
adversarial part of the network which
will judge it and give a score based on
like redo it again.
Sorry.
Yeah. Yeah. So um and the other thing
too is with uh gradient descent whenever
you do that um that backward the back
backwardation pass um it will go through
the adversarial part as well as the main
part. So the adversarial part will get
better as the the main uh part of the
model is better as well. So it adjusts
all of the weights across the board.
Uh all right, alpha proof and alpha
geometry.
So these were interesting because
uh this was where so back in the day we
had good oldfashioned symbolic AI
meaning that it was uh
so is lean like prologue. It's like a
fact based programming.
Sorry. Is lean like prologue? I've heard
of it. Is it like prologue in that it's
just like a fact based programming
language?
I'm not sure actually more like cog
for uh people watching through the
camera later who don't know.
There's a program called
So um
with the symbolic AI, good old fashioned
AI, right?
Um, as Josh and I have just we had so so
much discussion about like what do you
actually call that? I think we decided
like we we came down to uh algorithmic,
right?
See, I thought we were just talking
about what we call um
I don't know noni code in general which
I I tend to call procedural but
to be fair symbolic AI I wouldn't put in
the procedural bucket.
It's kind of a subset maybe
like subset of procedural in my opinion
using symbols.
Um so whenever I say symbolic AI kind of
that subset but also I'll I'll use
algorithmic code or procedural code what
I mean is your your classic like code
ifs and loops and uh decision um control
structures etc. So um
we kind of gone away from that because
we discovered neural networks and how
good they were at all of these crazy
things with machine learning.
Uh alpha proofs and alpha geometry were
kind of the return to that saying like
wait a second there might have actually
been some some stuff that we can take
from from those lessons, right? And so
what this was was essentially uh taking
a deep neural network and this is like
lots of people have done this um but
this is kind of like one of the first
ones that really like had an impact.
taking a deep neural network using the
the learning part of that and also the
generative part of that to kind of come
up with uh conscience,
right? And then that would be fed into a
procedural symbolic system to judge
that. And the reason why this works
really well is because with mathematics
and geometry there is no
have like that's maybe correct. No, it's
it's exact, right? But you can't really
uh it's the the mathematician who's
doing research, they they develop a way
to have hunches of like, okay, well,
what if we try this, what if we try
that? So, this is combining that the
learned making a hunch part of it with
the actual discrete you are right or you
are wrong. and
it it works to great effect. And yeah,
and and this could kind of be thought of
as like
um a little bit of uh combining systems,
which is essentially what we're getting
into with agents nowadays, right? Like
you're combining uh the agent harness, I
suppose we're calling it now. um that is
kind of a procedural code that is
wrapped around model prompts.
Any questions or conversation we want to
get into there?
Uh I guess have any um any big problems
been solved for the first time uh by
these narabolic systems or like at least
any famous ones I guess?
Uh yes. Um so
one that I can think of off the top of
my head is it's not alpha proof or alpha
geometry but on the alpha series it's
alpha evolve um solved for a it actually
solved a lot of things I think it had
like a
don't quote me on this but I want to say
that it was
uh
like 75% it would match the
state-of-the-art solution and 20% of At
the time it actually did better on a
certain set of math problems and the one
in particular uh was with tensors 4x4
tensor uh using an algorithm developed
by forgetting his name but um showing
that uh so he got it down to I want to
say it was 40
uh scalar uh scaler multiplications.
to do a 4x4 to multiply a 4x4 tensor by
a 4x4 tensor and alpha evolve I want to
say got it down to 46.
What is a tensor?
A tensor is uh simply a matrix. So a
matrix is a a tensor is the more
generalized form of it. So if you have
uh
matrix
and then
so if you have like
one three six whatever
um
this is kind of a matrix right it's a a
1D matrix also known as a scalar
and then you add another dimension to
that. So
you wrap all of these in brackets,
you have a square, right? So that is a
matrix. And then uh if you go to a
threedimensional object, so imagine this
goes out this way. You've got like or up
here in threedimensional space. Uh that
would be they're all tens, right? So I
don't know I guess a cubic maybe I don't
know the term for it but but both a
scalar and uh a matrix they're all
tensors. So tensors is like the
supererset of that kind of ordered set
of things on any number of dimensions.
Also,
I think I just misspoke. A scaler, I
believe, is uh zero dimensions. So, it's
one number and a vector is one
dimension. Thank you. You guys need to
call me out. Come on.
All right. So
all right. So excuse me. As I mentioned,
um
the the we were looking at kind of like
stacks of patterns in the previous
examples that actually produced real
world results, Nobel prizes. Um, so
we're going to dig in a little bit more
at the specific paradigms that those
facts are built on. And um, one of these
I'm very familiar with. Some of the
other ones uh, not much and speak of the
devil.
Um, evolutionary models are uh,
interesting in that they try to
replicate
uh, evolution as it happens in the
world. So natural selection and there's
a lot of different ways we do this.
So the one that I'm familiar with mostly
is a family in
who
I I don't know how to pronounce his last
name but um this is actually uh means a
lot to me because uh back in high school
whenever I started getting into this um
it was like 2004 my junior year the
thing that I came up with was genetic
algorithms. I didn't know they were
called that at the time, but that kind
of made the most sense to me for solving
an what to me was an intractable problem
of how do you make machine learn how do
you make it think
um this comes in lots of different
forms. So neat uh neural evolution uh
for
something
thank you. Um this is kind of the
architectural
uh part of it where you're starting with
a very very simple uh neural network and
it builds out piece by piece. So it's
very very foundational in that each step
of that is like adding to one little bit
at a time. And there's uh well first of
all let me take a step back and explain
what is meant by genetic algorithms. So
rather than uh having one model that you
train and do gradient descent or energy
base or however you do it, you're
basically trying you have a method of
adjusting it, right? Of trying something
new and then you have what's called a
fitness function. So rather than trying
something new once, you try something
new a thousand times, right? You do like
little permutations
and uh that is your population and then
you run all thousand of those against
your fitness function which is going to
say how good are you at doing whatever
the fitness function is solving for. It
might be predicting the next word or it
might be anything you can write a
function for, right?
Um and we'll kind of come to see that
the fitness function is really the bread
and butter of any kind of an
evolutionary system. But it judges those
um in a a basian way. So probabilistic
way of how good you did you do against
the surface function. Say a score from
zero to one a float from 0 to one. By
float I mean blah blah blah whatever.
um and it throws away all the rest. So
it might keep the top 10% of the
population or the top five or what have
you. Now say you take the top 10%. So
out of thousand you have 100. It will
then mix those and this is where um a
lot of the flavor of different
methodologies come into play where you
might have a genome which is simply a
way of saying a way to encode what each
of these models look like. Uh like
here's here's the layers that could be
considered a genome or here's the
architecture that's considered a genome.
Uh, so if you have some structured way
of doing that, then you can do
crossovers. So it's like having two
horses. I don't know why I'm with
horses, but let's go with it. Two horses
that have different traits that you
like. Um, those traits are their genome,
right? Just like in biology, and you
breed them together and you get some mix
of the two.
Uh, from there, there's other things we
can do. uh for instance with regular uh
uh populations as we go on generations
uh there's mutations right so you can do
uh random mutations on those flow what
that looks like is you could say out of
the 10% that we kept breed all of those
together until you get back to a
thousand and so that would be generation
two and actually you can keep the 10%
that were good so like you're breeding
to 900 more. Um, and then out of those
900 more that you made, let's actually
mutate a certain number of those, say
30%. So, out of those, take 30% of them
and actually do random mutations, random
pertubations. Uh, I don't think I said
that right, but whatever. Um, you know,
mess mess with them a little bit and see
like what happens.
And then we go again, we go through the
business function and you rinse them and
repeat. Now, Back in the day, this was
really hard to do because we simply
didn't have the compute. I ran into
compute walls all throughout 2008 to
like 2014 is whenever it really started
like coming up to where it's like
actually we can do this because you're
not just training one model. Especially
if you do a combination of uh gradient
descent in between these uh generations,
you're essentially training the entire
population of models. So rather than
training one, you're training a
thousand.
Now you can get around this. You can fix
some programs but not training them as
much until they get to complete
convergence. And also you're getting um
a probabilistic uh fitness from your
fitness function uh if you're doing it
right. So it's not just a you did it or
you didn't. How how close did you get?
Um,
so
there's a lot of So what what that
really gets down to is uh as long as you
can write a fitness function for
something, you can kind of evolve
something for it. Now therein lies the
big strength of evolutionary approaches
is that they can really solve for novel
things. I have no idea how to make a
program for this. Large language models
are not going to help me. How in the
hell do I solve for I don't know
helicopter flight like all the different
things of that? Well, I don't know.
Throw [__] at the wall and see what
fits. That's essentially what you're
doing. um over many many many steps and
eventually you get to a model that is
like I'm very good at propeller
aerodynamics or rotor aerodynamics or
whatever come up with stuff here but uh
cm
so neat is more of uh was kind of the
foundation of what we call NAS uh which
is neural architecture search um or ENOS
uh evolutionary neural architecture
first which is building up a model from
scratch.
Uh there's a lot of other things you can
evolve on besides the model architecture
itself. Um
and by architecture just uh so we all
know I'm talking about whenever you have
an input to a model and it goes through
the model there's like layers right you
can think of them as like walls and each
one of them can have different types of
uh neurons or perceptrons in there um so
you can build up the architecture or how
about we evolve on the weights
themselves
one of the ones that's really really
popular I think overly popular right now
is hyperparameter uh evolution and so by
hyperparameters what I'm talking about
are all of the kind of meta
configurations of a model such as
learning rate uh which learning rate in
the case of faster gradient descent
would be like how much it does how much
it steps each time how much better it is
each time because you can overshoot
there's all kinds of things that can go
wrong so finding that perfect uh
learning rate is important or we could
do any number of other hyperparameters
uh like there's the um the temperature
uh
thousands of things right
so one of these I think it's DMA yes so
it takes it with a grain of salt but
basically it does like boxes um it it
makes boxes for the different
populations and it shves uh those into
the boxes and rather than uh going over
the entire entire population. It will
select subsets of the population. Um,
another one uh that it kind of focuses
on meat uh or another aspect kind of on
meat and um and some of the other ones
is uh and one of the challenges of uh
evolutionary algorithms is trying to
keep a diverse population. Now, what I
mean by that is say you have a
population of fruit flies and you're
evolving them to uh be resistant to
alcohol. A common biological experiment
is done. Uh so say they do like one
small step that is a trait that will
make them better at being able to
survive an alcoholic environment.
um that trait, that little step that
they took might not be apparent uh in
the first generation.
So it might actually have different. So
those would get killed off even though
they were kind of on their way to
getting there. So what uh that looks
like with the diversification in uh
evolutionary approaches is essentially
some sort of like protection like
whenever you have a mutation in the
population. Uh one easy example would be
like let's keep it around for like three
or four generations to see how it does
before we just
I guess what I'm saying is like how
would you even know in that first one if
it did anything? you wouldn't because
you know it died and so if you're trying
to make incremental changes to something
even if those increments are happening
you know thousands of times in iteration
because you have all these models doing
different changes I feel like if you
don't actually see a visual a visible
change in the capability you're not
going to be able to have any
deterministic understanding of what it
actually
so these are kind of hard class rules
and what that might look like in
practice is you could have a threshold
of how much did it change, right? And if
it gets over that threshold, then we
just keep it around for three
generations.
So you have a threshold and if it change
like a very small fraction of a
percentage that's enough based on the
way you're trying to understand whether
the change you would accept it as like
heat to see what happens.
Yeah. So basically I guess kind of what
it looks like if you have um
you
I this is the one approach out of the
whole thing I've actually read about
when you do need one step is is
clustering them so that similar things
in a group and then letting the fist of
each group survive.
I actually I think that's uh CMA yes is
what you're describing.
But no no that that's that is what is
happening though. You're you're
basically um kind of doing that just at
the group level and so neat kind of did
that the same way and forgetting the
exact algorithm that they use in that
but yeah it's it's that
you might like hard code the number of
clusters that you are looking at right
yeah and so uh yeah you're jogging my
memory here in
in neat there was something it was
called speciation and so and that gets
into like what I was talking about with
the threshold of difference so if you
have like a population uh A B C you can
see each of these a different species in
that population. You go to generation
two and you have a sub one, a sub 2, uh
b sub one, b sub 2, so on so forth, c
died out, but it it sucks. Um, but then
all of a sudden with your mutation step,
you get uh another one
where whenever you compare the genomes,
which say each one of these have like a
genome like series of tags like what
describes it. I guess you didn't uh a
mutation that was big enough where if
you look at the the genome like a sub
one is pretty close to a sub 2 b sub one
is pretty close to b sub two I don't
know that right then this e thing like
what the hell is that okay we don't know
let's let's mark that and keep that guy
around for two generations so that it
doesn't die off we'll see what it does
um whereas you know you go through the
next generation you might have a
A3
A1 died off. Uh A4 A is doing pretty
good. We only have B1 because B2 died
off. But E didn't do so good, but we're
still going to keep it around. So he
stays
that kind of help explain it.
And would would the genome itself be
like the layers of the network like an
array of layers?
Yes, that it could be that it's anything
that you can kind of encode any kind of
like factual representation. Um, it
could even be like a a UID for each
thing and you could have some method of
uh modifying that UID a slight amount so
that you can kind of tell the genealogy
of the species.
So then the then the next thing is the
management of all the different clusters
so that it doesn't become odorous from
you as the person trying to conduct the
experiments.
Yeah. And so that's
algorithmically right
right that that would be like the uh
keep keep the top 10%.
That would be like the keep the top 10%
or keep the top 30% or whatever and then
you know basically mutate and breed out
until you get to a certain population.
And you bring up a good point because
you could have dynamic uh population
sizes. You could have dynamic amounts of
um
uh the population.
Uh you know, all of these things could
be more uh softer, more u dynamically uh
set. And we can kind of get into that
with the hierarchical approach um
whenever we get into like the research
talk. And if you no and if you have if
you have additional clock cycles or
whatever resource to be able to conduct
this, if you wanted to try and
potentially conduct a move 37 example,
you would possibly flip it and
algorithmically would do the other side
of it that you the other percentage that
you got rid of.
Yeah. I mean, there's a lot of different
things that you can do to kind of
randomize this, right? And um
uh
so so You could do uh even different a
different uh amount of mutation. So you
could say like take these 10% and mutate
them this much. Take these this 10%
mutate them more. Take this 10% mutate
like make them completely like wild
things, right? And see what happens.
Not to mention the the ethical
considerations of having alcohol
resistant fruit lives.
That's not how we usually kill fruit.
when when you mutate a genome in these
algorithms, are you basically flipping
one trait to the next or can you tweak
one trait
um or create a trait?
So,
it's kind of up to up to you. I mean,
there's any number of ways you can do
it. So, a good example would be like
layer crossover. So if you have uh like
you have a model and it has like say
five different linear layers in this
model and and five different linear
layers in that model or say like some of
those layers are different kinds of
layers like you have a convolutional
layer in there or whatever.
Yeah.
Whenever these two uh match together you
can randomly take basically zip them
together. You can take like layer from
this one layer from that one layer from
that one layer from this one. And that
can be any number of things. It could be
weights, just the weights or what we
call the thetas of the the parameters
and that would be basically evolving on
the weights
um or the hyperparameters like I said or
the model architecture itself or any
number of other things and when we get
into the hierarchal part you can kind of
evolve on different levels right so you
can evolve the architecture at one level
the uh hyperparameters on another level
if you have like a graph neural network
you can evolve the graph and the
underlying uh layers within those nodes.
Uh so in the in the natural context of
evolution the the other species are part
of the environment for each species in
each generation for example if the if
there are birds coexisting with your uh
seed eating mammal maybe your seed
eating mammal gets cooked but if there
are no birds it's the best at getting
seeds and it does well. So um so at
least in terms of like emulating nature
that would be an approach and it seems
like most evolutionary AI methods um
evaluate each individual in a generation
independently but are there any
techniques that take them or that I
guess are there any techniques where
each sample is not independent from the
others and it's sort of mixed up? There
are so for one I'm pretty sure the CMA
ES is kind of like that if it's in the
boxes but also we'll get into swarm uh
there's swarm approaches so the swarm is
very much that um
be
I think there's anyway
there's swarm methods where um
you could essentially think of it as you
that you could think of an ant colony.
And it's like, okay, well, we're going
to take this ant colony and we're going
to uh match all these ants together and
and breed more ants and and throw away
the population that sucks and keep good
ones. Then we eventually get like a
really awesome ant colony. The swarm
method would be look at each of these
ant colonies that like one level above,
right? Which one of these ant colonies
more? Okay. Well, let's keep these three
ant colon throw away those five. So
that's same thing. And the the really
cool thing is there's no limitation to
how deep you can go with that. Um and in
the the medium article I wrote back in
like 2024, I think I went over that a
little bit where it's like we have
population and then we have worlds and
we're going to look at the world and you
know multi level. So
is that slide read by quad camp?
the the last. Yeah, embarrassingly
parallel. That phrase is what tipped me
off. Claude loves saying that
parallelism
that's just like hacker newspap. I've
heard that like chat.
I don't know plot in particular. Like if
you're talking about anything that's
even a little bit parallel, it'll it'll
whip that out like every paragraph.
Sorry, that's a bit of a diversion.
That's all right. So, also like I said,
um I'll I'll give this repo out. Um,
I'll make it public at the end of this,
but I'm going to go back in and actually
clean this up because I kind of was in a
hurry, but I'll I'll go through and like
I'll put something in the read me or
whatever that says like, "All right,
I've gone through this. It's cool."
Parallel with dignity,
right?
Exactly.
All right.
Energy based model. So this one I'm not
as familiar with but uh it's kind of
like the meta representation or like
this form thing with evolutionary things
where you can think of an energy based
model as well let's go back to a token
prediction large language model right it
predicts the next word and then it feeds
that back in and predicts the next word
so you get word word word
um energy based models are more
predicting states
think of like the paragraph like how
close is this paragraph to what a a good
paragraph would look like? All right.
Well, if we're off by this much, let's
modify that paragraph to be uh a little
bit better. And you can think of this as
like an energy landscape. So, think of
like a topographical map and you've got
hills and valleys and the valleys are
like your states that are trained to be
ideal. And the uh input for that I using
paragraph as an example but it could be
anything. It could be a whole world
model like how much does this world
model make sense? every aspect of it.
Like it could be a gigantic
very very high dimensional tensor with
like gigantic vectors, right? Um or it
could be an image, right? We've got like
this. So it could and diffusion models
kind of work kind of like this actually
pretty similar where we've got this uh
static image. How much does this look
like real life IRL? Well, Not at all.
Okay. Well, let's take a step down and
instead of like stepping down to figure
out better network prediction, you're
taking the entire state of that that
two-dimensional RGB image, so really
threedimensional, and moving it closer
and closer into the valley where in the
valleys are the actual realistic
pictures.
This could be um
uh protein folding. It could be uh any
kind of like a representation of 3D
space. So the real strength of energy
based models is that you can really wrap
a lot of stuff into
uh each step of it getting better and
you're looking for the low energy uh
solutions in that landscape.
Uh
pop network I think is the most like
fundamental one. um where you're
basically take you can think of it as
like um you imagine like a piece of
aluminum sheeting or like metal
sheeting. You're taking like a ballpeen
hammer and hitting it making big dents
in it and each one of those dents is
like here's a representation that is
accurate. And so you go and you drop a
or like a marble onto that and it'll
roll around and eventually it'll roll
down into one of those things. Right? So
that's kind of a a hospital network, a
Boltzman machine. I have no idea. I'm
not familiar with that. So sorry about
that.
Uh Jeffrey Hinton,
uh
he got a Nobel Prize for his work in
energy based models and I and award.
Yeah. Yeah. Um so Jeffrey Hen is like
one of the grandfathers of AI. Um,
and was was he doing Yeah, he was doing
he might have been involved in both of
them, but he definitely
stuff, which again, I don't know a whole
lot about it, so I apologize for that.
Yeah. Okay. So, any questions on that? I
might not be able to answer them, but
how how is is what they're doing
different from like gradient descent
trying to like find the
uh I think it's really not that much
different except that you're doing it on
multiple different uh like rather than
doing it token by token, it's more of
like state by state and any number of
things could be in that state. Uh you
could have
essentially like uh
yeah and so it gets really complex and
but I I guess like uh right Jeffrey
Hinton did um he was the one that solved
the algorithm for backward propagation
uh the differential for that I'm pretty
sure like 90
yeah um and so I think it you're
basically doing that gradient descent
but you're doing it across the entire
state so it's very very computer heavy.
Um
I I think you do like a a
combination essentially like an average
to get the energy level of the entire
state once you do that. Um is it
possible that gradient kind of came out
of energy based methods like if it was
like a formalization of what they
possibly yeah I don't know.
Well, I think it was him that did the
solve for a way to efficiently do that
to solve for that background using the
differential to find the slope that was
allowed for that to actually be random.
Correct. I think that sounds great.
Yeah. Yeah. At least put it together.
But probably like the calculus or
something.
What the title of the paper?
Yeah.
Well, like the the evolutionary systems
going back to those like neat that was I
think 2004. Um, and I I kind of called
that like one of the foundational pieces
of it, but I think it was like the
late60s where we actually were really
first getting into genetic algorithms.
And I don't know who all was involved in
that, but a lot of these things have
been around for a long time and they're
kind of like resurfacing here and there.
And it's like, oh yeah, well like um uh
the uh transformer has been around the
non-quadratic linear version of
transformer has been around since I
think early 70s. Um, and before that
there was uh LSTM, long short-term
memory, which that was back in like I
want to say the early '7s as well. Um,
so and we're kind of coming back around
to see that with like X LFP.
Um,
yeah.
So parallel with this
approach.
Yeah, I think that's whenever the uh I
want to say his name starts with an R
but like Ryan or something came up with
the tinsert math for doing that the most
uh or the the method that is was like
the most efficient at the time that
could work across any x y or any
divisionality of I believe so Yeah,
neurosolic AI.
So this is more really just what I
mentioned with the uh the alpha proof
and alpha geometry. So it's just simply
the combination of uh neural networks
and uh symbolic algorithmic or
procedural code to judge that. You can
think of it as like uh the the neural
part of it is like taking a look, seeing
it, the hunch like what about this uh
almost like coming up with a state of
the input, right? And then you're
passing that along to the symbolic
system which is saying that's not
accurate. Change how you see things or
no that's actually pretty good. Yeah,
like continue doing that. Um so this is
just a combination of the two. Um and
symbolic uh all that is meant by that is
just like you can have a symbol for
something like uh Plato's uh world of
forms like a symbol for a triangle. This
is this is the absolute perfect form of
a triangle right that would be like a
symbol. Um so it's using those the
procedural code uh and kind of trying to
make the representation that way but
then using the neural uh the uh neural
network part of it to kind of do the
generative or like un guess part like
the novel the new forms if you think
All right.
Honorable mentions.
So,
um
create some trees. This is um this
essentially um um trees uh
drawing a complete blank. What's the um
the tree search that I used earlier?
Uh Monte Car
is essentially Monte Carlo search.
You're going down the decision tree and
you're uh boosting the uh the ones that
perform better and uh pruning the ones
that don't getting rid of them. uh
probabilistic and basian methods all
that is is uh having probabilities for
events. So rather than predicting the
uh the next word exactly and saying like
I mean large language models kind of do
this because they'll usually have like a
list of word predictions and the
temperature will kind of uh notate how
crazy they get with selection of that.
But I guess the real thing is like
instead of having one output, you might
have 10 outputs with probabilities
attached to each of those. Like this is
the most probabilistic next state
prediction, what have you, followed by
this one, followed by this one, followed
by this one. One of the uh shallow uh
machine learning algorithms called naive
base where it's essentially the same
thing, but you're not taking the
previous state. And so the the proper
basian method can get into a
combinatorial explosion by which I mean
this is way too much way too fast uh
exponential like trying to figure out
what to do or which way to go but
typically you'll get like probabilities
and then you'll go one step further and
get probabilities there and then you can
take the average of those probabilities
for like an actual population
Oh, through all of them. So, um
uh geometric and uh graph networks.
These are interesting graph networks.
So, it's essentially just adding another
layer. Um
is everybody here familiar with a graph
with nodes? Okay.
Essentially,
you're taking
uh pathways through a graph, which a
neural network is a graph, right? But
you're simply putting more into each
node. So, you can go down a pathway to a
node and within that node could be an
entire model. uh and with current neural
networks now there are sparks networks
where not every single uh neuron or
perceptron is hit there's mixture of
experts where it actually routes uh
different pathways through the model you
could think of mixture of experts as
especially spark mixture of experts as a
a kind of sort of graph neural network
in a way um because they don't have to
hit every node like it's a linear
linear layers, every single neuron is
outputting to every single neuron. Uh
it's called a dense dense network,
right? Whereas
graph neural networks, not only do they
not have to hit every pathway, but they
can be cyclic. So, uh you've got
directed as graphs where it's always
going forward, but it's not necessarily
hitting every single pathway. uh uh you
can have cyclic ones where it goes down
the pathway and then loops back around
to a previous node. And uh it's there's
a lot of a lot of uh uh at least
theoretical promise with these because
we really think that's kind of how our
human brains work, right? We've got
different uh structures within our brain
um that are responsible for different
things and you're kind of hitting each
of those in like different ways along
this track. Um,
right.
Um,
is isn't this uh one of the strategies
that Tesla said that they're trying to
use to dumb down the recent self-driving
stuff so it can work on the the older
cars because they've got like millions
of these cars that have their older
computer
and they were worried that the new model
won't fit. And so one of the things they
started doing is they were exploring the
idea of instead of looking at the whole
thing,
can you predict what part of the
situation is worth attention
and then direct your uh effort down just
those paths. So kind of like walking a
subset of the entire
Yeah. And I I don't know about the Tesla
thing. Most likely. Um I know you said
it so I'm guessing so but I've not wrote
that. You can also combine these too,
right? Like what you're talking about an
awfully lot,
right? So like if you have graph network
and you treat it as a research
um you can have multiple hierarchies
there. Well,
thank you memory. All
right. All right.
So state space models are
uh keeping state the entire state rather
than um
language models looking at like the
entire like word. So like we were
talking about earlier with kind of uh
getting rid of the context each time
doing a vector search to get what's
relevant and putting that into uh just
completely uh redoing the context for
that's kind of what uh state based
models do. So you can think of it as uh
rather than looking at the entirety of
the prompts and the word prediction and
like looping that back uh over and over
over again for the next word prediction,
you're kind of like taking a look at
that, taking down notes, like jotting
down notes in like a notebook, right?
And then you say, "Okay, what's next?
Okay, well from that I've got these
notes. Let's adjust my notes ever so
slightly this way to kind of keep up
with the current state of things.
Um,
active inference and free energy. Um,
so active inference is uh was kind of
the precursor to reasoning models. Uh,
this was like back in AR AGI 2024
challenge. uh
they we were kind of working um around
with doing test time inference where
you're basically
doing another level of inference as
you're outputting. So you can think of
that as like having the the reasoning
steps that also kind of looks like a
tree search, right? you're kind of going
down different reasoning paths and then
selecting which ones are best and then
using that as kind of like an addition
to the context
as you're answering the question. So
this is where reasoning models came from
um cellular automa
um
this is very similar to um evolutionary
approaches. So what it really means is
instead of having a fitness function
that is a more well- definfined thing of
I want to get to this in state it's more
of giving a world making a world an
environment right and then seeing how
like having a rule set for that
environment and letting things evolve
within that environment. So you don't
have one fitness function. You have a
whole kind of world model or like
environment model that has a rule set uh
to it of like oh this is a good thing.
You need to go get food. Um don't touch
the the red blob because that red blob
will kill you. Um and so a lot of the
evolutionary part of it is kind of
environmental based rather than just
based on the fitness function and the uh
the result of that.
and
neuro.
Yeah. Um,
yeah. Um, let me get back to you on that
because there are some really really
good approaches. Um, Wolram is a big
proponent of of this for sure. Uh, from
my my home stomping grounds, I'll
actually be seeing him. Uh, Champagne
Orana. So, he's actually from a few
different places, but
Oh, he's from Champagne, Illinois.
Yeah.
Oh,
well, not originally. I'm from further
south than that, but I lived in
Champagne uh for 11 years.
there.
Yeah,
it's a pretty cool town just uh
surrounded by cornfield. So,
um but yeah, there's some really really
interesting stuff that I've read about
with the whole cellular tea and that
sort of thing, but I can't think of it.
There's actually some really good
machine learning talk episodes on that
as well. So I'm not familiar with
cellular automa machine learning, but
would it be like you're morphing the
physics of the world that the are
are like progressing through? Is that
what you're changing?
So um that would be like having a kind
that would be like having a dynamic
fitness function. So you could have a
static uh environment and just be like I
want the best thing the best uh model
for this that can survive this
environment. Um you if you were to
mutate that environment over time that's
actually a really interesting uh kind of
novel thing. I say novel but I it's been
discussed but it hasn't been looked into
a lot. That's actually one of the things
that I've gotten into with my research
is like oh holy [__] business functions
don't have to be static. We can have the
orchestration part that changes them
over time which is exactly kind of what
that would be with the environment
changing that based on any number of
outside influence.
Yeah. In normal evolution, it would have
decided,
right? Things change. Uh the the niche
niche changes.
Um you know, global warming, earthquake,
hurricane, what you know, whatever. Like
a new predator is introduced, an
invasive species. Yeah. Um
neuromorphic.
Uh I actually don't really know anything
about that. So there's an honorable
mention. I can't really beat on as much.
Does anybody know anything about
uh I mean I don't I can't say I have any
deep knowledge. I can at least toss a
couple terms out there. Um so I know at
least some of it is the notion of a
meister which is a sort of a transistor
with memory hence meister and the idea
is that the um well a little bit like a
neuron it's uh
it activations are influenced by prior
activations in such a manner. Oh again
it's intended to resemble a neuron to
some extent.
And my understanding is that
neuromorphic computers um
well there's a variety of approaches.
The one I recently heard about was using
um
a lattice of bars that didn't anyone um
not the last term.
Uh it's
panels like solar panels.
Yes, they're used in solar panels, but
basically it's a class of uh molecules
that combine in the same crystal lice
shape that has the
I'm not really a chemist. I'm not going
to get into it, but um I have a very
clear like I remember what the diagrams
look like, but attempting to properly
describe it would be beyond my ability.
Um but essentially the the meristers are
sort of it's almost like having weights
in hardware that are influenced by
activations. And I think part of the
idea is that the in the brain um the
timing of activation is very relevant
for how a neuron gets used. And so
having all of this [__] directly
integrated into hardware is partially so
in a normal computer if you give the
same instructions or whatever you'll get
the exact same stuff back out but a
neuromorphic computer is inherently
stateful because each memory inside is
stateful right
it's really interesting because it's
almost like a graph neural network but
one that where you can be doing several
passes in parallel right but they might
not be perfectly in parallel they might
be like slightly async
So depending on the outsider variables
you can change like a computer you put a
program it spits in and out the same
thing but with a neuro neuromorphic it
sounds to me like the conditions can
change how it behaves kind of like a
person or brain or something.
Yeah I believe that is the case as for
whether they can be trained
I don't actually know how that works. I
know they change with each but
supposedly sort of u adapt but I think
there is a discrete training process at
the very beginning that works
differently from um from its day-to-day
operation but I don't really know
it's almost like the analog version of
having the different datas once
differently on
believe so
seems very cool but I have not given it
relatedly I uh I noticed you were
reaching out with the hints I mentioned
you had a touring award I have the paper
download it, but I haven't read it.
So, I wasn't sure if wrote that paper.
Yeah, I've listened to a couple of talks
uh
that he's done or like interviews that
he's done.
Um I don't know like a lot of history.
All right. Uh so, now we're going into a
different
kind of cool.
All right. So, Um, for the research part
of this, um, I'm going to kind of go
into the, uh, my thoughts. And again,
this is supposed to be like I wanted to
be an open discussion. So, this it
really is going to be us talking. I was
mentioning that, uh, I kind of made some
slides for this, but like no.
So, I'm just going to kind of leave uh,
this up and um, we can talk about it.
I'll probably show some of like the data
uh set that I'm using and kind of maybe
do some backgrounding on the board of uh
my thoughts on it. So to start out with,
as I mentioned, uh the back in high
school, I was kind of thinking about
like how in the hell would you solve for
uh intelligence, machine learning
because uh thinking about the symbolic
way of that we were doing things mostly
back then like this is not scalable at
all. Like you can throw uh thousands and
thousands of uh if then statements at
it. you can kind of figure out what your
symbols are, but that's still going to
be a lot more like human written code.
It's not going to be able to scale to
take into account the world model of
this
amazingly complex uh universe we live
in, right? So, how did we get here?
Well, we got here through evolution,
arguably, but not really.
So some people would argue I whatever
each their own. Um
and anyway I'm not uh so uh I started
working on genetic algorithms. I didn't
know they were called that at the time.
And what it kind of started out with is
a really really uh lame approach because
I was not that good of a programmer back
then. I was doing random permutations on
code and compiled. Um like literally
just random three mutations without any
real direction at all. Uh eventually
that turned into like oh I need some way
to test this and uh Grammarly was
actually around back then. So I started
uh I was feeding it in uh Mariam Webster
dictionary having it do mutations across
those or like uh uh basically putting
together those words and mutating the
programs how it would put together those
words and then checking it with
Grammarly to see well for one would it
even compile
and so it was written in C and two um
C++ and two um uh if it compiled, would
it give any output at all? And then
three, uh if it gave output, check that
against Grammarly to see if it actually
was made sense, if it was like
dramatically correct, and judge it on
how many mistakes there were. So those
were kind of like my three functions. Um
what I realized is that uh evolution is
stupid um in that it does randomly
mutate and if you give it millions of
years or in this case thousands and
thousands of hours of compute time it'll
eventually get there but without any
direction it's just randomly it really
just branched up the wall see right so
at that point uh I came across like Oh
well, it makes sense to actually have
some sort of like an orchestration layer
uh an orchestrator for the evolution to
kind of direct it a little bit more uh
towards those being able to solve those
functions. Uh I didn't want to use like
a heavy hand with that orchestration
because one of the ideas that I have is
that intelligence is not necessarily
uh specifically only the way that we
think of as intelligent as humans. Um,
you know, the classic example is an
octopus.
Octopuses are obviously intelligent.
They can solve a lot of real world
problems, but if you were to like look
inside the brain of an octopus or the
mini brains of an octopus and see its
actual thoughts, they probably would not
resemble human thoughts at all.
Yeah. Yeah. So the the uh the arms can
kind of work independently and it's all
connected. So I guess it's all kind of
technically one brain and also I'm not a
biologist but um I'm speaking out of my
my wheelhouse here. But yeah, it's
something like that. It's it's
definitely not a human brain, right?
Okay.
Um,
and you know there's any number of other
kinds of things that you could consider
intelligent. Is is the internet
intelligent?
I mean there's a lot of information
processing that happens there. It's made
by intelligent creatures. And so uh we
have mimemetic things that pass through
the internet uh ideas uh being spawned
created obviously driven by human uh
well human and AI now but previously
human uh creation but in this different
substrate that is constantly changing
constantly evolving in this complex
system in and of itself so is that not a
form of an intelligent system
question right so the idea is that there
are many different forms of intelligence
and uh I didn't want to narrow down to
just human intelligence.
Uh going on from there after the
orchestration part
uh one of the things that I realized is
that you can do this in hierarchies.
So um what I mean by that is if you are
evolving a species from a population to
solve for a problem, why not also solve
the world?
Why not break it down into
uh solar systems or whatever you know
different uh method of uh hierarchy you
want you want to use example but the
idea is to have multiple levels of uh
orchest multiple hierarchy for with each
level evolving uh in parallel you mean
like multiscale intelligent like a cell
is intelligent in its own right but then
it forms a tissue and tissues form an
organism Exactly. And that's a very
common way that I would think about it
as in like we are intelligent systems.
We are composed of a bunch of cells and
bacteria. Um even looking back at like
mitochondria, right? It was made by at
least our best guess which we're pretty
sure about now is it was two bacteria
two protoone bacteria that merge
together and a symbiotic relationship
where they eventually fuse into one
thing that has become fused into us as
the powerhouse of cell
meme.
Um so yeah it's exactly that. Um
different levels there and uh which
obviously takes a lot more compute as
well. uh kind of the the next step that
I realized is that um
uh actually what we were talking about
earlier with your uh changing
environment
was that you can make the fitness
functions dynamic
uh in that you can change them over
time. The orchestrator can be like okay
now we want to go this direction that
direction and what that solves for is
generalization. um that allows uh the
evolved model to generalize more to be
able to take whatever is thrown at it.
So you get a new a new task, a new
problem and it can shift the fitness
functions and solve for that. And then
uh the next step was for me to break it
down into parts. So what that looks like
is you have you have a problem and it
kind of can look at that problem and say
do we have a solution for this problem?
Uh no. Okay. Well, kick off the
evolutionary part and so it will try to
evolve uh
like a single layer uh against that
problem to see if it can come up with a
model that will solve for it. If not
after a certain threshold, it will break
into a second hierarchy and so you build
up those layers uh at a certain point of
layers um which you can set as one of
these hyperparameters. It will then uh
say okay this is a really hard problem
obviously. So then it will look at the
problem itself and it'll break that up
and it will make it will run the
evolutionary algorithm on each part of
that problem. And what this is solving
for is uh what is commonly called
priors. So in order to solve a problem
you might need to have a given number of
priors. Right? This might be
for uh using the ARGI challenge. Uh are
are we familiar with the ARGI challenge?
Everybody?
No. Okay. So the arci challenge is uh
was made by prim
and um
are you using RKGI as a environment to
evolve
your project?
Uh not currently and uh I will get into
that in a little bit because it's kind
of broken off into now it's kind of
going to be three parts.
Um
uh oh here we go. Okay. So essentially
you're given
you're given a subset of like uh here's
this like grid. This is for RGI1
RG3 but uh you're given this grid and it
turns into this. Given this grid, it
turns into that. You're given this grid.
What's your current state? Um so what
it's meant to do is meant to have
problems that humans can easily solve
but that uh take abstract reasoning and
priors that uh AI is find really really
difficult. Uh RPGI1 that benchmark went
for I think it was like six years with
people throwing everything at it and it
just was not able to solve.
a prior in this case like there are some
ones some some of the puzzles that solve
like will demonstrate gravity for
instance or objectness being able to
differentiate one object from another.
So that's what I mean by prior uh
basically the most minuscule uh gate or
thing that you need to solve for a
certain part of the problem. So
uh yeah, so what we're doing is we're
breaking down the problem into smaller
uh uh atomic pieces of that problem and
we're evolving a model for each of those
uh more simplistic things to solve and
then we are doing an ensemble of those
mini models plugging them together into
a chain that will solve each part of
that problem. Uh and now what we do from
what I do from there is once we get that
ensemble
uh which eventually ends up looking kind
of like a graph neural network because
it can have each layer of the hierarchy
in the evolutionary system will
essentially be like a node um or like a
graph and then the level below it will
be a node of that graph. um we kind of
take that pack it into a known solution
and we put that into a DSL of different
solution. So it kind of looks like
program synthesis but with these evolved
little mini models. Um that's the idea
anyway. Haven't quite gotten there yet.
Um because I realized that
one of the main problems with that is
that it doesn't have good knowledge
representation in in work in other words
it doesn't have a good world model so
that's where I broke out uh al also like
in all my years of doing this um I
didn't realize that uh modern uh large
language models and most models the
encoding layer is part of the model as a
whole. Now
I'm going to put that on pause for a
second because we're going to get back
to that for Nexus. I'm forgetting one
important part of the whole like
evolutionary approach that span going
over the years. It was around like 2009
to 2011 or so that I first discovered uh
neural networks. Uh the first one was um
forget the name of it was library before
TensorFlowJS.
What's that?
ReinforceJS or
no? Um
I I'll get back to that uh at some point
if I can't remember it. But anyway, I
found neural networks and I'm like, "Oh,
this is like a whole new thing. This is
crazy. like I can mesh this into my
symbolic uh and algorithmic approach and
have kind of soften the edges of it a
little bit. Um so that's where I
actually started seeing a lot more
progress is using those uh neural
networks as the evolved pieces rather
than shifting around actual like pieces
of code.
And so
uh
so so you you're evol you have you're
evolving little models that could solve
like like one model might solve that
another one might solve another arc AGI
puzzle and then somehow orchestrating
them together to kind of coordinate who
solves what and when.
Is that am I understanding that right?
So like you might have like a total
model that that can solve just about
anything. assuming you've trained enough
of these like smaller scale models kind
of like so for like one level of the
hierarchy like we'll call it the third
level
um yes that would be the case of like
this is the one that is like evolving
models um with these underlying
hierarchies or collections of models for
the ARGI composition as a whole then one
level below that it would be like per
problem
like in this case uh taking into account
like all of these and then one level
below that this is a pretty simplistic
one of the ARPI challenges
but the the lowest level might be
actually like taking and looking at
these like uh square by square being
like what changed in this one what
changed in that one change in that one
and I also tried out like some
metalarning strategies and doing weird
things where I was like taking these and
making a threedimensional space out of
them and looking at that uh basically uh
taking these and like stacking them
together and doing 3D convolution over
that
for like metalarning and all kinds of
weird experimentation. But yeah,
essentially like it would be you you
break down the problems wherever you see
fit too and that is kind of where the
human judgment comes in a little bit and
kind of uh the manipulation of that
orchestrator orchestrator or
orchestrator. what what are you using to
like perceive the problem like the
perception layer? Um, and I guess the
perception layer could be the
orchestrator or could feed into the
orchestrator, but when when you see a
problem, what how are you passing that
in to the system?
So, you're actually touching on the
exact problem that I ran into, okay,
is creating the world model.
Um, and so that's going to be where we
get into Nexus, which we can jump into
now. The role model is like what problem
the capability is trying to solve,
right? It's like identifying who the
characters are, what the actors are, the
setting and the pro the problem set that
the capability is trying to
provide answers to.
All of the above except for the uh the
problems the solutions of what it's
trying to solve for. Now there's a lot
of nuance in this answer because a lot
of world mod like vja
um are trying to predict uh the next
thing um so whereas what I'm doing is
not necessarily uh taskbased or task
oriented other than
placing other than the knowledge
representation um basically placing that
in the vector space in the proper way
across modalities where uh everything
involving that concept is pointing to
the same place which I can get into how
the decoder. You're you're encoding.
Yeah. And and so that's kind of what I
was getting into where I realized that
the encoding layer uh is a part of these
models and that makes sense because
or it has one major pro in that the
encoder gets better as the model gets
better because the encoder itself is
part of the back propagation. Right? So
if it encodes something the wrong way
and it produces the wrong model output
as you do the backward propagation, it's
adjusting the weights of all of the four
task levels layers of that model but
also the encoder itself.
So if you split the encoder apart from
the model, you lose that because the
encoder doesn't get any better if the
model's wrong. But you can make just the
code, right? And so that's what nexus
gets into where I'm like, all right,
let's keep this completely separate. And
you actually, this is all hypothesis
now. Um, but you get a lot more pros
than cons uh of doing that. For
instance, you can hypothetically train a
lot of task oriented models downstream
of the world model that are all using
that world model as the filter where
they all kind of have um the same
substrate. We talked about this on
Discord a little bit.
They all kind of have the same
substrate, shared substrate that they
are the same language they're speaking,
right?
without having to encode decode from uh
language tokens into sensors and back
and forth. Yeah. Um and so that's
actually what I'm working on right now
is
are you starting from a pre-trained
encoder encoding model and then doing
like a on top of it or are you starting
from like are you training from scratch?
Training from scratch. So and the reason
for that is because I'm uh doing a
neural architecture search from uh like
I'm not only going to do uh the
evolutionary approach with the task
oriented uh models but I'm also using
that for the uh the encoder itself. So
that's what you saw where I was taking
out uh different layers and kind of
intermixing them. Um,
and so
here's the data set that I'm going off
of.
That's really hard to see with the uh
the black background, but if you go on
to hugging face and look for Nexus
temporal hierarchical multimodal
uh you'll get this and essentially
a terabyte of data.
It's like 542 gigs.
So this is derived from 2,00 uh videos
from hugging based fine video.
Okay. And uh what I've done is I've gone
through and broken this piece down into
temporal steps. So right here, I wish
this was not cut off. Um but
You're a part.
So
we've got
slices.
Uh this is at the lowest level. And so
you can see that we have um
uh the video ID is more of like metadata
and then we've got an index start
millisecond. Um, and as you can see,
these are 10 millisecond slices. And we
have the audio, we have, uh, the index
of the frame, uh, and the index of all
of these, uh, experience, minutes, text,
uh, imu for acceleration, uh, GPS, temp,
humidity. And so this is what I was
talking about with it being extensible,
uh, to be across any number of
modalities that you want to be. Um,
obviously we don't have data for this
right now, but uh I used the uh Montreal
force aligner as part of the process of
breaking down these videos. So basically
I'm breaking it down into uh each frame
and getting the uh the 16 bits uh audio
from
from that 10 milliseconds
right here. And then uh I I don't think
we're even at the the phone part yet,
but breaking the words down into the
phone names.
Yeah.
And then as you go up in levels, so we
go from uh slices like moments.
Um and you can see these are 100
milliseconds each and then up into
seconds
which are obviously a second each up
into
uh experiences in seconds
so on so forth. And then if we look at
the
let me get my
Yes.
Monad.
Um
I thought it was a play on Nomad.
So
that but also there is a a function
program.
I think you're right.
Okay. Whatever.
All right. So,
oh, hey, it's already on the
So, I broke it down into that data set,
but as we can see here, um, it's
actually
uh it goes higher than just minutes. So
it will go through
from slice to moment to experience
episode to hour to day to year to
decline.
And each of these uh is tied together so
that it really is tree structure. You
can think of it as like at the very
bottom you've got all these like 10
millisecond slices and then above that
with a link down uh to each of them
you've got the next level up so on so
forth.
So where did you find the thousand years
right? Uh oh yeah yeah I gotcha. Um so
we don't have that much video yet but
the idea is to um it's going to be
representing making knowledge
representations across this scale. So
everything is going to be in the like
millennial millennium is going to be
well really century is but like it's
going to all have hyperplanes going
across all of it right so this is kind
of like like I have the modalities as
extensible where we can have uh
it's ambition.
It's ambition. Yeah. It's it's it's
future proofing. Um
uh and it's just to kind of complete the
link like you know ideally this would go
up to you know heat death of the
universe but or big rip or big crunch
but forever.
Yeah. Um but the idea is that we are
basically taking these
uh architecture choices
which
it's been like since February since I
Yeah. So, I guess it is kind of these.
So, like we've got a bunch of different
uh kind of network pieces um
well, whatever. But, um basically It's
going through like this selection of
different layers and it's just randomly
plugging those together and seeing how
it does. And the idea is to um basically
line up if you have um something like an
apple,
you have uh the word apple written out a
ple. You've got uh the word spoken, the
sound apple. You got pictures of apples,
images of apples, the sound of whenever
you crunch into it. Uh, all of these
kind of should point to the concept of
Apple.
And so what it's doing is it's evolving
and judging on um how well it can relate
different pieces across that temporal
tree to say like, oh, these like 10
slices uh relate to this moment, relate
to this experience, so on so forth up
the tree. And that creates a hyper plane
through that temporal structure of uh a
relationship or relation which we can
see here. Um and there's a few different
ones that I have kind of predefined um
where we have like uh
causal is like
you you eat an apple and then it becomes
eaten, right? Or whatever. Um
compositional would be uh like apple and
apple tree and apple seed and so on so
forth. Um bobing for apple.
Yeah. Yeah. Um would be kind of like an
association, right? But it goes through
and it makes these uh these this hyper
plane of relations relations between the
different uh nodes in the temporal tree
where uh
each one and each relationship can be a
combination of those nodes in the
temporal tree, but it can also have
relationships in it as well. like you'll
see um um
um so okay so if there's like a slice
that captures like the first phone of
apple like someone's starting to say it
are you saying like the the encode
encoded vector of that should be
somewhere close to the word apple that
might be captured in like a moment or a
um could be but because going to look
across all these different modalities.
Um, it is actually going to have like
the frame of the video in there as well.
So, if it looks at that same phone name
and it doesn't see anything like an
apple in the frame,
uh, it can actually down uh down that to
where it's like, okay, this is the same
phone, but it's not the same, like it's
not going to create a relationship
between that and uh the other ones that
are Apple
and actually there's the relationship is
a whole um kind of like intermediary
uh step in between that the different
parts of the temporal tree and the final
thing which is the concept concepts.
So concept is a collection of concepts
and relationships. So it can have a
concept can have concepts of it in
itself but also relationship pointers.
And so you can think of all this as like
um
a uh link list of
know basically
uh a hierarchy of links.
And so uh
basically I'm thinking that
once we get once I get to this being
like well done and kind of explored I'll
be able to use this as that filter to
have taskbased
uh evolutionary models following the
same kind of algorithmic approach that I
uh was describing where I can break down
problems time prior have a solution set
of uh different preassembled
pre-ensembled
uh solutions and all of that put
together I think is going to be the very
beginning of a good foundation for me to
start looking into consciousness
because I'll have an actual real
underlying representation of what the
world is. all have evolved models which
could be any manner of intelligence not
human defined uh to kind of solve for
those things and from there I think we
can start looking into how to wrap that
into like now observe yourself how do we
create
anyway
so okay so I'm still trying to
understand like the temporal aspects
here um So like like the slice would be
one level of link twist and the moment
would be another level of link twist and
and then you have like a like hyper
planning almost of of that going through
longer segments of time. Um yes so the
slices are definitely a link list. The
uh the moments are also link list but
they also have pointers. So each moment
is going to have pointers to the slices
below it and they can also have
additional data as well. So like you've
got the phone at that level and then you
go up and you eventually get to like um
seconds and you'll have words and then
you go up to experiences and whole
sentences you know as kind of like an
additional layer. And so that's where it
can actually make those relationships
between like here is a sentence that
involves the actual apple and it's going
to be related to that a phone or a
And then we've got this other one that
has the same or but we're talking about
um Apollo mission, right? So that's
probably not related and it's through
that it can kind of figure out like okay
these two phones even though they're the
same are not actually there's no
relationship there.
Yeah.
And is um the structure of the data set
where they they reference like through
like temporally down um is that is that
so you can train a single encoder and
keep like the representation of of the
idea or the concept
in multiple scales of time or um are you
training like a separate encoder for
each scale?
Uh there's I've tried different ways.
Okay.
Um That's a great question. Uh I've
tried both ways. I think right now as I
have it, it is actually a single encoder
that will take the entire so uh as a
slice comes in, it will actually look
all the way up the tree um to and
basically do an encoding for that entire
line from line down through the
single slice. Um, and it actually Yeah,
because I I have it to where like it
know like um it I actually had to do a
recursive function to know whenever it's
going to go from like one moment to the
next and then from one experience to the
next to be able to kind of line this up.
Whenever I get this finished, by the
way, this is all going to be part of the
paper and open source, but right now is
not.
When I work on stuff like this, I find
that
the nuance differ.
I'm looking at this model that you have
highlighted for example
whatever type uh you have strength and
confidence
in your mind. Why do you have two versus
uh one concept like what makes one
different from the other
if it's an experiment just you know
yeah I'm I'm thinking back to doing that
um trying to remember it's been since
like February I worked on this
um
not sure
I can take the code
You don't have to curious because like
those are the hard questions for me.
It's like the meaning of a word as I'm
like trying to build a model because the
model is a simple stage. And so if I'm
simplifying it, that's where I feel like
I have to get hyper clear about what it
is I'm exactly trying to express.
Could it uh could it have been that um
strength would like a strength of zero
and confidence of one would mean I am
positive that these two things are not
at all related? Strength one.
Yeah. Like so so strength is like
how strong that like pathway is between
the two and then the confidence I would
be like how sure you are of that
and I I think I that's used in the
confidence if you okay yeah so I think
the strength is used in the structure if
I'm remembering right and the confidence
is actually used uh to store kind of the
result
right I'm actually going to be diving
into this over the next two days and to
try to get this all wrapped up and done
so at that point if you ask me I'll be
able to tell
after your trip.
Well, before my trip is uh so I'm going
to try to get it finished um over this
long weekend that we have so that it's
ready to go for whenever I fly out on
Yeah. Well, I have to figure that
on.
Sorry.
Yeah, hopefully. Um, I'm not going to be
presenting on it. I'm going to um
call it an assembly. And I don't really
know what to expect yet because it's the
first one of its kind, but uh it's we're
going to be kind of
completing uh some formalization into
the study of machine consciousness
research and
um I'm thinking that's going to be more
like working groups more than just
speakers. Uh I'm not sure.
All right,
that's all I got.